-==破烂熊乐园倾情奉献==-
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-==http://www.ragbear.com==-
是,首相 第二季第8集
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译&校对：tpring
时间轴：色色
盘根错节
伯纳 我们伟大的政治家今天下午如何?
Bernard, and how is our great statesman this afternoon?
他挺开心的
Well, he's very cheerful.
哦? 他什么事这么开心?
Really? Where did he found to be cheerful about?
这次质询他应付得很不错
Well, at Question Time he did very well.
是吗 谁说的?
Indeed. In whose opinion?
都这么说
Well, Everyone
窃听议员电话的事他答的很精彩
was impressed with his answer on tapping MPs' phones.
对 我听说了 可惜不是听你说的
Yes, I heard about that, but regrettably not from you.
这...我以为没必要通报
Well...I didn't see any point.
伯纳 我统筹整个政府保安工作
Bernard, I coordinate all government security.
这个问题怎么没先向我汇报?
Why was the question not referred to me first?
这是意外问题 临时加的
It was an unforeseen supplementary.
这是意料之中的意外问题
Well, It was a foreseeable unforeseen supplementary.
可答复不错啊
But it was a good answer.
"尽管我极其重视下院的意见"
"Much as I respect and value the opinions of this house,
"我必须承认 尊敬的议员们说的话"
I must confenss I have no desire to listen to the word
"若非工作需要 我一句也不愿多听"
honourable members for any longer than actually I have to."
哄堂大笑      你笑的吧
It got a quite good laugh.        From you.
有我 还有他的政党
Yes, and from his own party.
那些想升官的
The One's hoping to be promoted
还是那些怕丢官的?
or the one's afraid of being sacked?
这就全包括了
Well, just about all of them.
我猜他矢口否认授权了
I gather he denied that he'd authorised
窃听议员电话吧      是呀
the bugging of an MP's phone.        Well, yes.
他没授权吧? 是吗? 他有吗? 糟糕
Well, he hasn't, has he? Has he? He has? Crikey!
都在这了 伯纳 包括转录文本
It's all here, Bernard, including the transcripts.
我们去...
Shall we...
不能过一会再去吗?
Well, Can't we wait a bit longer?
他这种自得其乐的机会不多
He doesn't get many moments of unalloyed pleasure.
他也只配有这么多了
I suppose he gets all he deserves.
快进来 汉弗莱      首相
Come in! Humphrey.        Prime Minister.
我想谈谈您接受质询的事
I want to talk about Prime Minister's Question Time.
谢谢 我接受你的祝贺
Thank you. I accept your congratulations!
我答得很妙吧? 你不觉得吗?
Wasn't I brilliant? Didn't you think so?
我不在现场 不过...
Well, I wasn't there, but...
哦 汉弗莱
Oh, Humphrey
我答得妙吧 伯纳?
Wasn't I brilliant, Bernard?
我相信下午您的回答
Well I believe your replies this afternoon
一定让他们过耳不忘
will not be quickly forgotten.
我来讲给你听 汉弗莱
Let me tell you what happened, Humphrey
第一问是关于内政部
The first question was about that home office cock-up
典狱官短缺的丑闻 我答得天衣无缝
over the shortage of prison officers. My reply was Masterly !
我说 "请尊敬的议员参考一下"
I said, "I refer the honourable member to the speech I made
"我10月28日的下院讲话"
this house on October 28th."
他记得您讲了什么吗?
Did he remember what you'd said?
当然不记得 老实说 我都不记得
No, of course not. Neither did I, come to that.
不过堵上他的嘴了
Still, it shut him up.
接着是失业率
The next one was about our employment
"就业部是否在玩弄数据?"
"Whether the Department of Employment fiddle the figures?"
您是说
You mean
定期重组收集数据的基础条件
periodically restructure the base from which the statistics
而回避了公众视线?
have been derived without drawing the public?
是啊 玩弄数据嘛      当然有
Exactly. Fiddle the figures.        Well, of course they do.
我知道他们有
I know they do.
可我说的是 我尚未发现确凿证据
But I said I'd found no significant evidence of it.
因为您没问嘛
That's because you haven't looked.
我们也没告诉您
And because we haven't shown you.
我知道 干得好
I know. Well done Humphrey.
然后又是一记阴招
Then we went straight on to a googly about
貌似攻击能源部的核废料处理计划
the Dept of Energy's plans for disposing of a nuclear waste.
其实是想诱我承认 内阁已经分化了
The question was tried to get me to admit Cabinet was divided.
是分化了啊      我知道
Well, it is.        I know that.
所以我说
So I said,
"我的内阁决议都是全体一致通过"
"My cabinet took a unanimous decision."
因为您威胁说
That's only because you threatened
谁有异议就开除吧
to dismiss anyone who wouldn't agree.
结果果然全体一致了
It certainly made them agree unanimously.
我每说一句 我的后座议员都欢呼雀跃
By this time, My back benchers were cheering my every word.
哦 对 下一个问题是
Oh, Yes, then we had a question about
为什么我们花了大钱的
why since we spent so much money on it
反导弹导弹出厂前一天
our new anti-missile missile was scrapped as obsolete
会全部因为过时而报废?
the day before it came off the production line.
您又是怎么岔开的呢?
And how did you wriggle out of that one?
岔开? 这是我最得意的一个
Wriggle? That was my masterstroke!
汉弗莱 简直是神来之笔
My reply, Humphrey, was sheer genius.
我说我们的政策没达到预期效果
I simply said our policy had not been as effective as we'd hoped
显然当初制订错了
Clearly we had got it wrong.
您承认啦?      是啊 很天才吧?
You admitted that?        Yeah. Brilliant! Wasn't it?
立刻就让他泄了气
Took the wind right out of his sails!
在下院里说实话总能唬住人
Honesty always gives you the advantage of surprise
让他们措手不及
in the House of Commons.
临时又会有人问首相
There was actually a supplementary the Prime Minister was asked
什么时候会让负有责任的大臣
when he would request the resignation
交辞呈
from the responsible minister.
好办 我说我会要他辞职
Too easy. I said I'll ask for it the resignation
"等他犯了错误 有人抓了现行"
"When he makes a mistake that could've been seen at the time"
"而不是乱放马后炮的时候"
"and not with the benefit of hindsight."
他们高兴得一蹦三尺高
They were on their feet cheering,
手舞足蹈 议程纸满天飞
stamping, waving their order papers!
我听说
I gather
有个问题问的是窃听议员电话
there was a question about the bugging of an MP's telephone.
对啊 这个可把大家乐坏了 我说...
Oh, Yes, I got a terrific laugh with that. I said...
我知道 伯纳告诉我了
I know Bernard told me.
我说 "尽管我极其重视..."
I said,"Much as I respect..."
对 我知道 伯纳告诉我了
Yes, I know. Bernard told me.
好吧 反正问的也够无聊的
Oh. Well, anyway, that was just stupid.
我们干嘛要窃听哈利法克斯的电话?
I mean why should we bug Hugh Halifax's telephone?
何必呢 他可是我自己的人
Happens to be one of my own administration!
他们怎么会冒出这种念头?
did where they get such a daft idea?
被害妄想狂      对 问题在于...
Sheer paranoia.        Yes, The only thing is...
我说 我们何苦窃听大臣说话?
I mean Why should we listen in to MPs?
无聊 愚蠢 自以为是
Boring, stupid, ignorant windbags!
能不听我都求之不得
I do my best not to listen to them.
他不就是个政务次官么
And he's only a PPS.
连我都查不出来
I have enough trouble finding out
国防部在搞什么鬼 他能知道什么?
what's going on at Prime Minister's Defence. What could he know?
就是说
So I gather
您否认窃听了哈利法克斯的电话?
you denied that Mr Halifax's phone had been bugged?
当然 今天就这一个问题我可以
Obviously, it was the one question today to which I could give a
清晰 简明 利落地说出实话
clear, simple, straightforward, honest answer.
是啊 可惜 尽管您确实清晰
Yes, unfortunately, although the answer was indeed clear,
简明 利落 您最后一个形容词的
simple and straightforward, that is some difficult in justifiably
适用性却值得商榷
assigning the 4th term you applied to the statement...
具体体现在 要如何联系
....in as much as the precise correlation
您公开传达的信息
between the information you communicated
和迄今为止已知的事实
and the facts insofar as they can be determined
同时您的表述方法又造成了规模可观的
and demonstrated is such as to cause epistemological problems
认识论难题 从而使其
of sufficient magnitude as to lay upon
对英国语言的逻辑和辞义
the logical and semantic resources of the English language
加诸了它们普遍无法承受的重担
a heavier burden than they can reasonably be expected to bear.
认识论? 你在说什么啊?
Epistemological? What are you talking about?
您...撒了个谎
You... told a lie.
撒了个谎?      撒了个谎
A lie?        A lie.
什么叫"撒了个谎"?
What do you mean, a lie?
就是说您...
I mean, you...
撒谎了 是啊 我深知
....lied. Yes, I know
你们政治家很难理解这个概念
this is a difficult concept to get across to a politician.
您...
You...
对了 您没说实话
Yes, you did not tell the truth.
你是说 我们真的在窃听他的电话?
You mean we are bugging Halifax's telephone?
窃听过      几时停止的?
We were.        When did we stop?
...17分钟前
...17 minutes ago.
这不能叫撒谎吧
Well, you can't call that lying!
您说诚实的反义词是什么?
What is the opposite of telling the truth?
可我又不是故意的
But I mean, there was no intent.
我从不故意
I didn't mean to deceive them,
误导下院的
I never knowingly mislead the House.
无论如何 您确实误导了
Nonetheless you have done so.
不能怪我 我又不知情
Wasn't my fault. I didn't know he's being bugged!
首相 人们认为您知道
Prime Minister you are deemed to have known
按理该您负责
you're automaticly responsible.
怎么没告诉我?
Why wasn't I told?
大概内政部长不觉得有必要通知您
The Home Secretary might not have felt the need to inform you.
为什么?      大概他也不知道
Why?        Perhaps he didn't know either.
也可能有人建议他 您没必要知道
Or perhaps he'd been advised that you did not need to know.
可我有必要知道啊
Well, I did need to know.
显然 当时并不知道您有必要知道
Apparently the fact you needed to know was not known at the time
您知道它的必要性 我们现在才知道
that the now-known need to know was known.
也许
Therefore,
给内政大臣作参谋的人认为
those needed to advise inform the Home Secretary perhaps felt
鉴于他尚且不知道他有必要知道的
that the information he needed as to whether to inform
是否该向最高权威部门汇报
the highest authority know the information was not yet known,
因此没人授权将情况汇报给高层
and therefore was no authority for the authority to be informed
因为知道它的必要性当时
because they need to know
并不知道 也不必要
was thought that time not known or needed.
什么?
What?
我们不知道您会在下院否认它
We could not know that you'd deny it in the House.
要是我不知道 被问到了当然会否认
Obviously I would if I didn't know and were asked.
我们不知道您不知道的时候会被问到
We did not know that you'd be asked when you didn't know.
如果我不知道
I was bound to be asked
被问到的时候当然也不知道
when I didn't know if I didn't know!
什么?      什么?
What?        What?
当时的考虑是 不告诉您为好
It was thought that it was better not to inform you.
您看 哈里法克斯是您政府的一员
You see, Halifax is one of your government team.
因此当时觉得 最好不要制造猜忌
As such it was thought it was better not to create distrust.
您有必要了解时 我们才通知您
We only tell you when you should be aware.
那是几时?
When's that?
现在就是了 因为您刚刚否认了
You should now be aware because you've just denied it.
我得在否认之前知情才有用啊
It would've been helpful if I'd been aware before I denied it.
正相反 首相 如果您否认前知情
On the contrary Prime Minister, If you had been aware
您就不会否认了
before you denied it, you wouldn't have denied it.
可我有必要知道
But I needed to know!
我们并不总告诉您窃听的事
We do not always tell you about bugging when you need to know.
您看 首相 有时候我们需要您不知道
You see, at times,Prime Minister, we need you not to know.
你凭什么决定瞒着我?      我没有
Why did you decide I didn't need to know?        I didn't.
谁瞒的?      没人瞒
Well, Who did?        Nobody.
只不过没人决定告诉您罢了
It was just nobody decided to tell you.
那不是一样
Well, it's the same thing!
恰恰相反 首相
On the contrary, Prime Minister.
决定向您隐瞒信息
To decide to conceal information from you
责任重大 任何官员都担不起
is a heavy burden for any official to shoulder,
可决定不向您透露信息
but to decide not to reveal information
只是工作惯例而已
to you is routine procedure.
汉弗莱 我有必要知道一切
Humphrey, I need to know everything.
一切?      一切
Everything?        Everything.
很好
Very well.
本周文具采购清单 48包...
Stationery deliveries this week. Four dozen packets...
得了 汉弗莱 别胡扯了
No, Humphrey, Humphrey, don't be silly.
我是说重要的一切
I mean important things.
谁来决定什么重要呢?
Who should decide what is important?
汉弗莱 这个漏子你到底怎么解释?
Humphrey, How can you possibly defend this cock-up?
正如您在下院里说的 我们搞错了
Well, As you said in the House, we got it wrong.
是你搞错了
You got it wrong.
我 首相?
I prime minister?
我不过是个卑微的公仆 小吏而已
I am merely a humble servant, a lowly official.
这是内政大臣的决定
The Home Secretary made the decision.
你有什么理由
Can you think about a reason
能让我不逼他辞职么?
why shouldn't I ask him to resign?
恕我直言 首相 您不能逼他辞职
With respect Prime Minister you should only ask him to resign
除非他犯错误被人抓了现行
when he's made a mistake which could've been seen at the time
而不能因为马后炮
not the benefit of hinesight.
不过首相 这次还有个原因
But you see the trouble today has a reason
是您一时糊涂 亲口作了否认
because of your error of judgement in making this denial.
什么?
What?
您就不该否认您不知道的事情
You shouldn't have denied something about which you didn't know.
这怪你
That was your fault.
你承认有事瞒着我的
You just admitted keeping secrets from the Prime Minister.
绝无此事
Not at all, Prime Minister.
首相 体制能够完美运转
The system works perfectly well
只要首相先通知公务员
as long as the Prime Minister tells the Civil Service
他要说什么 然后才公开说
everything he's going to say before he says it.
可如果他贸然说了什么
But if, precipitantly, he says something without first
没有事先找我们核对 那他咎由自取
clearing it with our official, he has only himself to blame.
不经核对 您什么也不能说
You must not say anything public without clearing it.
恕我直言 首相 您得学会谨慎
With respect, Prime Minister, you must learn discretion.
我不知道有什么可谨慎的啊
I didn't know there was nothing to be discreet about!
政府中总有要谨慎的东西
In government there's always something to be discreet about.
再说 我们窃听哈里法克斯干嘛?
Anyway, why are we bugging Hugh Halifax?
他和俄国私通吗?
Is he talking to the Russians?
不 是和法国 这严重多了
No, the French, actually. That's much more serious.
为什么?
Why?
俄国人早对我们知根知底了
The Russians already know what we're doing.
可法国是我们可信的盟友啊
But the French are our trusted allies,
不管你有什么意见 谁没有呢?
whatever you think of them. And who doesn't?
不 首相
No, Prime Minister,
其实法国是我们可疑的盟友
actually the French are our mistrusted allies.
有鉴于此
That is why
和法国直接对话本身
talking directly to the French is regarded as prima facie
被外交部视为叛国行为
an act of treason by the Foreign Office...
是他们授权的
who authorised it.
我不知道啊      您...不知道什么?
I don't know.        You... don't know what?
我不知道谁授权的 谁授权的?
I don't know who authorised it. Who authorised it?
这里有回声吗?
Is there an echo?
汉弗莱 谁授权窃听的?
Humphrey, Who authorised this bugging?
外交部 我刚刚说了
The Foreign Office! I've just said.
总之 言多必失
Anyway, the less said the better.
您不觉得吗 首相?
Wouldn't you agree, Prime Minister?
关于什么?      关于一切
About what?        About everything.
显然 我不能拒绝下院委员会的质询
Obviously one cannot refuse to appear before a committee House.
不能 汉弗莱爵士
Well, no, sir.
显然 得告诉他们一切
And Obviously one shall have to tell them everything.
一切他们自有办法查到的事
Everything they can find out from other sources.
正是 可他们大概会问我
Precisely. But they are likely to ask me
首相是否曾经授权
if the Prime Minister's ever authorised
窃听议员电话
the bugging of an MP's telephone.
那么 忠诚的公仆该如何应对呢?
So how should a loyal public servant reply?
您可以说 这得问首相
Well, you could say it was a question for the Prime Minister
或者外交大臣 或者内务大臣
or the Foreign Secretary or the Home Office.
或者事关国家安全 您无可奉告
Or it was a security matter not liberty to confirm or deny.
如果我岔开问题 伯纳
If I dodge the question, Bernard
你知道他们接下来会问什么吗?
do you know what the next question will be?
为什么我不能作出明确否认
Why will I not give the same clear denial
像首相昨天在下院那样?
that the PM gave the House yesterday?
那我怎么说呢 伯纳?
And what should I say then, Bernard?
您可以说
Well, you could say
首相对此知道得比您多
the Prime Minister knows more about it than you do.
那人人都知道我撒谎了
Then they'd know I was lying.
那您打算怎么办?
So... what will you do?
我不知道 伯纳
I don't know, Bernard.
我只是觉得你也该为难一下
I just thought you should be aware of the dilemma.
来杯雪利酒吗 伯纳?
Would you like a glass of sherry, Bernard?
好呀 谢谢(甜的)
Oh, yes, thank you. Sweet.
只有原味的
There's only dry.
对了 伯纳 今天上午BBC来电话了
It's incidentally, Bernard, the BBC rang this morning.
BBC知道了?      当然没有 伯纳
The BBC know about it?        No, of course not Bernard.
他们想请我上一个纪实专访
They want to interview me for a documentary
广播3台的 谈谈政府结构
they're making on Radio3 about the structure of the government.
天啊 您不会去吧?
Gosh. You won't do it, will you?
为什么?
Why not?
他们没准要您说话呢
They may want you to say things.
广播一般就是干这个用的
That is quite normal on radio.
不不 我是说有趣的话 争议话题
No, no, I mean interesting things. Controversy.
话说回来 伯纳
On the other hand,Bernard
澄清事实 人人有责
one has a duty to put the record straight.
您是说您要去?
You mean you want to do it?
当然不是私心使然
Well, not for oneself, of course.
不是因为好为人师
No inclination for petty vanity,
想要扬名立万之类
you know, being a celebrity.
不过 做人不能谦虚过度
But... one can be too self-effacing.
我们这些人不该抛头露面吧
I thought we were supposed to be faceless.
上广播不用露面
They don't show your face on radio.
他们说如果我不去 阿诺德答应会去
They've said if I don't do it, Arnold has said he would.
也许那样更好
Perhaps that would be better.
阿诺德?
Arnold?
要是为我自己 我倒宁愿不去
For myself, I would rather not do it.
可责任感不许我坐视阿诺德
But I think one's sense of duty compels one to see that Arnold
被树立成优秀公务员的典范
is not held up as an example of a top civil servant.
您得找首相批准
Well, you'll need clearance from the Prime Minister.
对      不过那不成问题
Yes        But that won't be a problem.
你怎么知道?
How do you know?
广播3台嘛 反正没人听
Well, it's on Radio 3. Nobody'll be listening.
首相      汉弗莱
Prime Minister.        Humphrey.
请过目内阁议程 首相
The Cabinet agenda, Prime Minister.
你的专访是今天吗?      对啊
Is it today you do your interview?        Oh, yes.
有问题吗?      没有没有
Any problems?        Oh, no, no, no.
应对刁钻问题的方法我倒略知一二
I have some experience in dealing with difficult questions.
如果你敷衍塞责 绕弯子
If you're evasive or confusing on the radio,
他们只会剪掉
they edit you out.
你得说点什么才行
You've really got to say something.
说点什么?
Say something?
要说得明白 还要有趣
Something simple and interesting.
明白 还要有趣
Simple and interesting.
也许您能给我些建议 首相
Well, Perhaps you could advise me, Prime Minister,
尤其在问题带挑衅性的时候
particularly if the questions are aggressive.
那更好啊
The more aggressive is the better.
听众会同情你的
That puts listeners on your side.
不过 我总得回答吧
Nonetheless, I may have to answer them.
为什么? 我提问你就从来不答啊
Why? You've never answered my questions.
不不 这是两码事 首相
No, no, no, that's different, Prime Minister.
路德维克-肯尼迪可能会问些
Ludovic Kennedy might ask me some
内行的问题
perceptive questions.
他的研究中提到 很多人想问
His researchers mentioned that  lots of people are interested
为什么我手里集中了这么多权力
to know why so much power is centralised in my hands.
很多人?
Lots of people?
没几个人听过你吧 汉弗莱
Hardly anybody's ever heard of you, Humphrey!
也许他们是说很多广播3台的听众
Perhaps they meant lots of Radio 3 listeners.
这不是自相矛盾嘛
That's a contradiction in terms!
好吧 如果他真说很多人想知道
Still if he does say that lots of people want to know
你就说 "举出六个"
the answer to that question, you say, "Name six."
保证他没辙
That'll fix him.
他决不可能记得两个以上
He'll never be able to remember more than two.
太妙了 首相 还有别的花招吗?
Oh, excellent, Prime Minister. Any more tricks?
花招 汉弗莱? 这叫技巧
Tricks, Humphrey? This is technique.
抓住一个词攻击 比如"频繁"
Attack one word in the sentence. Like frequently.
"频繁? 什么才算频繁?"
"Frequently? What do you mean, frequently?"
或者攻击主持人
Or attack the interviewer.
像 "显然你根本没看白皮书 不是吗?"
Say "You've clearly never read the white paper, have you?"
或者自己提个问题
Or else ask your own question.
比如 "这个问题问得好"
Like "That was a very interesting question."
"现在让我问你一个问题" 你瞧
"Now let me ask you a question." See?
多谢您 首相
Thank you, Prime Minister.
这倒提醒我了 我最近会
Incidently, That reminds me, I have shortly
接受一个委员会质询
to appear before the committee to answer questions
回答关于窃听议员电话的事
about the alleged bugging of an MP's telephone.
对对 伯纳告诉我了
Yes. Yes, Bernard told me.
你证实我在下院的发言就行了
Well, you'll just have to confirm what I said in the House.
可那是撒谎啊      天知地知
But that would be lying.        Well, nobody'd know.
"哦 我们编织的错综复杂的网啊" (司各特 1808)
Oh, what a tangled web we weave.
汉弗莱 你非说不可
Humphrey, you must.
不然就成了我撒谎了
Otherwise it'll look as though I was lying.
汉弗莱 你得忠诚
Humphrey, you have a loyalty.
我忠于事实
To the truth.
抱歉 首相
I'm sorry, Prime Minister
我不能参与这种卑鄙的欺骗行为
I cannot become involved in some shabby cover-up.
反之 在对国家的
So whereas there must inevitably be
治理过程中
some element of shared responsibility
难免会产生某些共担的责任
for the governance of Britain,
介于立法者
as between the legislators on the one hand
和行政人员之间
and the administration on the other,
在任何事件中 原因之于结果
the precise allocation of cause to consequence or agency
或曰手段之于终局 其具体分界
to eventuality in any particular instance
盘根错节 乃至于虚无缥缈
is invariably so complex as to be ultimately invalid
难以承担责任
if not irresponsible.
我明白了 不过您能具体谈谈吗?
Yes, I see, but could you be a bit more precise?
我是问公务员系统在多大程度上
I mean how far is the Civil Service to blame
要为失业负责?      对 当然
for the present level of unemployment?        Yes, of course,
"失业"这个大而化之的媒体用语
unemployment is a single name applied by the media
囊括了五花八门的社会经济学现象
to what is a wide range of socio-economic phenomena
从政治上看 最明显的表征恰恰是...
whose most politically visible manifestation happens to be..
对对 您能不能再具体些...
Yes, I see. Could you be a little bit more precise...
不好意思 肯尼迪先生
I'm so sorry, Mr Kennedy.
是您向我提问的 请让我回答完
You've asked me the question. Do allow me to answer it.
谢谢
Thank you.
实际上 全国失业登记处每周
Happens to be a current frequency of weekly registrations
会按规定收到登记数据汇总
on the National Unemployment Register
人们认为
which is deemed to be above
它已经高出史上可接受水平
what has been held ought be an acceptable level.
不过哪怕理清各种综合原因
But even separating out the component causes,
更不用说为其单独归责
let alone allocating responsibility for them,
在统计学上意义都十分微妙
Is a task of such analytical delicacy
无法在一个热门
as not to be susceptible of compression
广播节目的范围中 完整加以阐释
within the narrow confines of a popular radio programme.
汉弗莱-阿普比爵士 非常感谢您
Sir Humphrey Appleby, thank you very much.
如果这算热门节目
If that was a popular programme,
冷门节目得什么样啊?
what would an unpopular programme be like?
谢谢 汉弗莱爵士 太精彩了
Thank you very much, Sir Humphrey. Absolutely splendid.
承蒙夸奖 讲的还行吧?
My pleasure. Was I all right?
您真的不能
Well, Couldn't you have said
多讲讲失业问题吗?
a bit more special about unemployment?
讲什么?      比如...实话
Such as?        Well... the truth.
有什么好笑?
Why do you laugh?
亲爱的阿路 关于失业没人会讲实话
My dear Ludo, nobody tells the truth about unemployment.
为什么?
Why not?
因为人人都知道 失业率减半只需几周
Well, because everybody knows you can halve it in a few weeks.
怎么做?      只要不发社保金
But how?        Cut off all Social Security
给那些拒绝了两次就业机会的人
to any claimant who refuses two job offers.
北方倒真有些失业者
There's genuine unemployment in the north,
可南方遍地都是懒汉
but the south England is awash with layabouts,
大批人大学一毕业
many of them graduates
就吃救济和住房补贴过活
living off the dole and housing benefit
还偷偷摸摸挣大笔外块
plus quite a lot of cash they pick up without telling anybody.
您是说 不见天日的私活?
You mean moonlighting?
光天化日还差不多
Well, sunlighting, really.
大多数雇主都抱怨缺人手
Most employers will tell you they're short-staffed,
可你要招扫大街的
but offer the unemployment street sweeping job
洗碗的 那些人拔腿就跑了
or dish washing job, they'd be off the register
骂他们"寄生虫"都来不及
before you could say "parasite".
老实说 失业率只会越爬越高
Frankly, This country can have as much unemployment
只要国家继续在社保金上烧钱
as it's prepared to pay for in Social Security.
没一个政客有勇气改变现状
and no politicians have got the guts to do anything about it.
这话录进节目就好了      那可不是
Oh, I do wish you'd said that.        I'm sure you do.
汉弗莱爵士      进来吧 伯纳
Sir Humphrey        Oh, come along, Bernard, come along.
要这个干什么?
I'm sorry, what's this for?
BBC刚给我送来了带子
The BBC have just sent me this tape.
似乎是我专访的录音片段
Apparently, it's part of my interview.
他们说简直太有趣了
They say it's particularly interesting.
您的专访?
Your interview?
你不相信我能说得有趣吗 伯纳?
You're surprised I should said something interesting, Bernard?
不不不 我只是以为您
Oh, no, no, Sir Humphrey, it's just that I thought you
打算像平常一样 什么都不说 呃...
intended to say nothing, as always. I mean...
打开听听 伯纳 你会受益良多的
Switch it on, Bernard. You may learn something.
亲爱的阿路 关于失业没人会讲实话
My dear Ludo, nobody tells the truth about unemployment.
为什么?
Why not?
因为人人都知道 失业率减半只需...
Because everyone knows you can halve it...
只要不发社保金给那些
Cut off all Social Security to all claimants
拒绝了两次就业机会的人
who refuse two j'ob offers...
没一个政客有勇气改变现状
And no politicians have got the guts to do anything about.
汉弗莱爵士 这不是您吧?
Sir Humphrey, that wasn't you, was it?
是我 伯纳
Yes, Bernard.
可您怎能说这种话?
But how could you say such things?
后面还有吗?
Is there any more?
有 伯纳
Yes, Bernard.
都这么有破坏性吗?
As damaging as what we've just heard?
还不止呢
More damaging.
我记得似乎说了... 寄生虫
I believe I referred to... parasites.
您怎能这么不谨慎?
How could you be so indiscreet?
访谈已经结束了
The interview was over!
我们在聊天 这不是官方记录
We were just chatting harmlessly! It was off the record!
都录在带子上了
It was on the tape!
老天啊 我明白了
Oh, my God, I've just realised!
敲诈      敲诈?
Blackmail.        Blackmail?
念念
Read that.
"这是您访谈中非正式的部分"
"Here is a copy of your off-the-recordpart of the interview."
"我们觉得太有趣了"
"We found it very interesting."
"我们将很快与你联系"
We will contact you shortly.
他们想要什么呢 伯纳?
What do they want of me, Bernard?
BBC? 收视费涨50%?
The BBC? Licence fee up 50%?
没准是制作人私下里敲诈
Maybe it's a private blackmail by the producer.
没准      他不知道我多穷吗?
Maybe.        Doesn't he know I'm a poor man?
也许他不了解您那一穷二白
Maybe he hasn't read you live in abject poverty
一年81000镑的生活
on 81,000 a year.
伯纳 我该怎么办?
Bernard, What am I going to do?
今后嘴巴放严实点
Well, keep your mouth shut in future.
你也一样 伯纳
And so must you Bernard!
不许跟任何人提一个字 任何人
I don't want you to breathe a word about this to anyone! Anyone!
我有责任告诉...
My duty to the...
伯纳 我会...
Bernard! I will...
伯纳 我该怎么办呢?
Bernard, what am I going to do?
也许您应该在媒体上发个声明
Well, perhaps you should put out a press statement
对失业者表示同情
expressing sympathy for the unemployed.
同情?      您就快加入他们了
Sympathy?        Well, you may be joining them any moment.
怎么了 伯纳?
Yes, Bernard?
抱歉 首相 您忙吗?
Excuse me, Prime Minister, are you busy?
能不忙吗 汉弗莱马上就来了
I suppose I am. I'm expecting Humphrey in a minute.
我得决定怎么向内阁交待
I've got to decide what to tell the Cabinet
窃听的事 要告诉他们实话...
about this bugging business. Do I tell them the truth...
还是咬定我在下院的说法?
or do I tell them what I told the House?
恕我冒昧 首相
Prime Minister, if I may venture to suggest,
您指望内阁怎么对您
Perhaps you should behave to the Cabinet
您就该怎么对他们
as you would expect Cabinet to behave to you.
有道理
Yes, you're quite right.
我得咬定在下院的说法
I'll tell them what I've told the House.
还有事吗 伯纳?
Something else, Bernard?
对 有件事您有必要知道
Yes, there is something else you need to know.
有必要知道?
Need to know?
对 是关于汉弗莱爵士的专访
Yes, it's about Sir Humphrey's broadcast.
无聊吧?      开始是的
Boring?        Initially, yes.
后来渐渐有趣了
And then it livened up immensely
他越来越口没遮拦了
as he became more and more indiscreet.
汉弗莱? 口没遮拦?
Humphrey? Indiscreet?
唉 他以为采访完了
Well, He thought the broadcast was over.
就随便聊聊 可带子还转着
He was chatting unofficially, but the tape was still running.
这种老套花招他都上当?
He fell for that old dodge?
对 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
凡是麦克风
You should always treat every microphone
都应该当成开着的
as that were live microphone.
他连这都不懂?
Doesn't he know that?
据我所知 他不常上广播
Well, I don't think he's done a lot of broadcasting.
老天 那他说了什么?
Oh, dear. What did he say?
他说 失业率随时能减半
Something about being able to halve unemployment tomorrow
只怪政府没那个胆
but the government hasn't the guts.
什么?
What?!
他不知道在录音啊
He didn't know he was being recorded.
母带在BBC手里?
And the BBC has the original?
你知道后果会怎样了
You know what this means, don't you.
明早的报纸头条啊
It means all over the papers tomorrow morning.
快想想办法 伯纳
You must do something, Bernard!
首相 其实我已经解决了
Well, actually Prime Minister, I'v already done it.
我刚和制作人吃了午饭
I'v just set lunch with producer.
他是我牛津的同学
He and I were Oxford together.
他根本没打算播出 所以我找他
He never had any intention of releasing the tape, so I got him
要来了带子上不谨慎的段落
to give me the indiscreet bit from the master tape.
这是母带?
This is the original?
汉弗莱知道你拿到了吗?
Does Humphrey know you've got it?
要我告诉他吗?      为什么?
Shall I tell him?        Why?
他肯定很想知道      那还用说
I think he'd like to know.        I'm sure he would.
可他有必要知道吗?
But does he need to know?
您是说有人有必要知道 可您知道
You mean somebody needs to know, but now you know,
汉弗莱爵士没必要知道
Sir Humphrey doesn't need to know.
可您有必要知道汉弗莱爵士不知道
But you need to know Sir Humphrey doesn't know,
可他没必要知道您知道
but he doesn't need to know you know,
或您知道他没必要知道
or that you know he doesn't need to know.
多谢了 伯纳
Thank you, Bernard,
真是提纲挈领啊
I couldn't have put it less clearly myself.
您想听听带子吗?
Would you like to hear the tape?
这东西怎么播?
Can you play this?
不 不是那个 我让他帮我转了一盘
Oh, no, not that. I got him to give me a copy.
且慢 我说
No, hold on a minute.
独乐乐不如众乐乐
I think this deserves a wider audience.
汉弗莱应该一起听
I think Humphrey ought to hear this.
喂? 是汉弗莱爵士
Yes? It is Sir Humphrey.
无巧不成书啊
What a happy coincidence.
请他来见我们 伯纳
Ask him to join us, would you, Bernard.
稍等一下好吗?
Will you hold on a moment?
首相 我告诉您的事都要保密
Prime Minister, I did tell you all this in confidence.
当然 伯纳
Of course Bernard.
我会尊重你的保密意识
And I respect your confidence.
这事很严重的 伯纳
This is serious, you know, Bernard.
对 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
汉弗莱爵士
Sir Humphrey.
汉弗莱 快快请进
Humphrey, come in, come in, come in!
电台专访如何啊?
How did your broadcast go?
不错 还不错
Oh, very well, very well.
你谈了什么?      就泛泛谈了谈
What did you say?        Oh, nothing in particular.
我记得指出了某些事不容易
I think I pointed out some of the difficulties in allocating
在政治家和公务员间归责的问题
responsibilities as between politicians and civil servants.
你谈的很谨慎吧?
But you were discreet?
干吗这么问?
Why do you ask?
到底有没有谨慎?      是的
Were you or weren't you?        Yes.
"是的"是有还是没有?      是的
Yes, you were or yes, you weren't?        Yes.
小汉?
Humpy?
您不觉得我会谨慎吗?
Wouldn't you expect me to be discreet?
那当然      那不就得了
Yes, Of course.        There you are, then.
好啊 这么说没问题了
Good. Well, that's all right then, isn't it.
干吗这么问 首相?
Why do you ask Prime Minister ?
没什么 BBC刚给我一盘带子
Well, It's just that the BBC sent me a tape.
带子 什么带子?
A tape? What tape?
你广播的带子
A tape of your broadcast.
我觉得该请你一起听
I thought we might listen to it together.
不行不行      怎么不行?
No, no, no, no, no!        Why not?
讲的没意思      没意思?
It isn't all interesting.        Not interesting?
内阁秘书向全国讲话?
The Cabinet Secretary talking to the nation?
没多大意思
Not very interesting.
你是说你太谨慎了?
You mean you were too discreet?
放出来吧 伯纳?
Play it, would you, Bernard?
亲爱的阿路 关于失业没人会讲实话
My dear Ludo, Nobody tells the truth about unemployment.
为什么?
Why not?
因为人人都知道 失业率减半只需几周
Because everyone knows you can halve it in a few weeks.
怎么做?      只要不发社保金
How?        Cut off all Social Security
给那些拒绝了两次工作机会的人
to all claimants who refuse two job offers.
北方倒真有些...
There's genuine unemployment...
汉弗莱
Humphrey!
真对不起 我不知道啊
I'm terribly sorry Prime Minister.I didn't know!
他们瞒着我 采访结束了
They didn't tell me the interview was over!
乱开簧腔
The indiscretion!
不负责任 还有吗?      没了
The irresponsibility! Is there any more?        No.
有
Yes.
接着放 伯纳      不...
Play it, Bernard.      No
拔腿就跑 骂他们"寄生虫"都来不及
... be off the register before you could say "parasite".
老实说 失业率只会越爬越高
Frankly, this country can have as much unemployment
只要国家继续在社保金上烧钱
as it's prepared to pay for in Social Security.
没一个政客有勇气改变现状
And no politicians have the guts to do anything about it.
这是你说的?      这是学口技的
You said that?!        It was Mike Yarwood.
这种事我可为难了
I'm in somewhat of a difficulty as to know
怎么办呢 汉弗莱
what to do about this, Humphrey
我需要建议      建议?
I think I need advice.         Advice?
也许该放给内阁 听听他们的意见
Perhaps I ought to play it to the Cabinet, get their reaction.
哦 求您      或者枢密院?
Oh, please!        Or the Privy Counsel.
哦 别
Oh, please!
不如给女皇?      上帝啊
Or... Her Majesty?        Oh, God!
你知道这个上了报纸
Do you realise what this would made if it got into the papers
对我和政府破坏力多大吧?
the damage would do to me? to the government?
我可以说我弄错了
Well, I could say I got it wrong!
我查证了 这不是真的
I've checked and it isn't true!
可这是真的      我可以说它不是
But it is true.        I could say it isn't!
没人能证伪 又没人试过
Nobody can prove it, it's never been tried!
你要对公众隐瞒真相?
You well tell an untruth in public?
对 为了您 首相!
Yes, for you, Prime Minister.
我们可以发个澄清声明
We can issue a clarification.
我觉得你已经说得够清楚了
I think you've already made yourself very clear.
不 首相
No, Prime Minister,
澄清声明不是让人说清楚的
a clarification is not to make oneself clear,
是把人洗清白的
it is to put oneself in the clear.
"哦 我们编织的错综复杂的网啊"
Oh, what a tangled web we weave.
把带子给我 伯纳
Give me the tape, would you, Bernard?
我有件事要告诉你
Now I've got something to tell you.
这是翻录的
This is a copy,
可这是原版 是母带
but this is the original, the master.
您是说...      从BBC取回来的
You mean...        They were retrieved from the BBC.
谁取来的?
By whom?
情报人员
Intelligence.
那么...别人不会知道了?
So... no one else will ever know?
这得看我怎么跟他们说了
Well, that rather depends on what I choose to tell them.
当然 我可以直接还给你 或者...
Of course, I could just hand over the tapes or...
我可以先拿着 考虑一下安全问题
....I could hold onto them while I consider the security
和政纪问题
and disciplinary implications.
我可不想参与什么
I certainly have no intention of joining
"卑鄙的欺骗行为"
"some shabby cover-up".
这倒提醒我了 你想好怎么
Oh, that reminds me, have you decided yet what you'll
跟特别委员会说了吗?
tell the Privileges Committee?
对 首相
Yes, yes, Prime Minister.
我想好了 为了国家安全
I've decided that, in the interests of national security,
唯一正直的办法是
that, the only honourable course is to
证实您在下院的说法
support your statement in the House.
说哈利法克斯的电话从未被窃听?
And say that Hugh Halifax's telephone has never been bugged?
说我没有证据...
And say I have no evidence...
不行 汉弗莱
No! Humphrey!
说政府从未授权过
And say the government has never authorised
窃听议员电话
the bugging of MPs' telephones.
说... 政府从未授权...
And say... the government has never author...
万一他们发现真相呢?
Supposing they find out the truth?
那你只需说没人告诉你
You'll just have to say that nobody told you
因为你没必要知道 好吗?
because you didn't need to know. Agreed?
太好了 就这么定了
Splendid. Well, That's settled, then.
带子可以物归原主了吗?
May one have one's tapes back?
明天
Tomorrow.
特别委员会质询完之后
After the Committee on Privileges.
好吗 汉弗莱?
All right, Humphrey?
是 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
"是,大臣"&"是,首相"系列全剧终
感谢大家19个月以来的支持
欢迎来破烂熊论坛发表观后感
收集本片完结纪念电子书 周边资料
以及关注其它好片
破烂熊字幕组
-==http://www.ragbear.com==-
欢迎加入